<?xml version="1.0"?>
<root>
  <trials>
    <trial>
      <main>
        <trial_id>RBR-9ngb95</trial_id>
        <utrn>U1111-1221-4052</utrn>
        <reg_name>REBEC</reg_name>
        <date_registration>07/11/2018</date_registration>
        <primary_sponsor>Universidade Federal de São Paulo</primary_sponsor>
        <public_title>Effects of calcium supplementation in the prevention of preeclampsia in hypertensive pregnant women.</public_title>
        <acronym> </acronym>
        <scientific_title>Effects of calcium use to evaluate efficacy and safety in the treatment of pregnant women with gestational hypertension: randomized clinical trial.</scientific_title>
        <scientific_acronym> </scientific_acronym>
        <date_enrolment>29/06/2018</date_enrolment>
        <type_enrolment>actual</type_enrolment>
        <target_size/>
        <recruitment_status>Data analysis completed</recruitment_status>
        <url>https://ensaiosclinicos.gov.br/rg/RBR-9ngb95</url>
        <study_type>Intervention</study_type>
        <study_design>It is a double-blind, randomized, controlled, double-blind, double-blind clinical trial.</study_design>
        <phase>N/A</phase>
        <hc_freetext>Pregnancy-Induced Hypertension</hc_freetext>
        <i_freetext>The intervention consisted of prescribing 02 calcium tablets containing 500 mg per day for the minimum intervention group (GIMin), 02 calcium tablets of 1,500 mg per day for the maximum intervention group (GIMax) and 02 placebo tablets for the placebo group. (GP). The placebo tablet was indistinguishable from the calcium tablet in appearance and taste and prescribed dosage.
Randomization was performed by a non-trial statistician using an online calculator via permuted blocking. Treatment assignments within blocks were determined randomly, in order, with the desired allocation ratio achieved within each block 1:1:1. The generated codes were allocated in the envelopes containing the information respecting the sequence generated by the randomization.
Participants were randomly allocated and blinded as to the dosage received from the 20th week of gestation until delivery. A third person (not masked) was responsible for administering and prescribing the pills. Study investigators were not masked for calcium measurement as masking does not interfere with the primary outcome of this study consisting of clinical and laboratory measurements.
Pills were provided to participants at each study follow-up. It was recommended that calcium be consumed with water, preferably between the two main meals (lunch and dinner) to minimize possible interference with the absorption of other minerals. No participant received antihypertensive treatment during the study period.
Participants were instructed to continue with supplementation until delivery, being asked not to change their normal food intake during the study and not to take supplements other than those provided by the investigator.
Envelopes containing the pills were given to the participants with the exact amount of pills for four weeks. After the first assessment (base line), sequential assessments took place 4 weeks after the start of the trial and 8 weeks after. Thus, every 4 weeks, new pills were offered and the clinical parameters and laboratory tests collected (blood and urine samples) were evaluated. Follow-up follow-up took place until delivery.
Once recruited, the participants were asked to return to the study site, on a day and time scheduled by the researchers, after a 12-hour fast, for clinical evaluation and collection of laboratory tests. The clinical evaluation consisted of the application of a research questionnaire containing demographic data and socioeconomic factors (age, schooling, income) in addition to a food recall questionnaire. During the clinical evaluation, anthropometric measurements were carried out, as well as the assessment of blood pressure levels, weight and collection of blood and urine samples. Thus, repeated observations were obtained over time for each participant, comprising baseline, 4 weeks, and 8 weeks.
In the recruitment and allocation of 193 eligible participants, 05 were excluded before randomization for not meeting the inclusion criteria, 11 refused to participate and 02 had severe anemia. Thus, 175 pregnant women were randomized and randomly allocated into 3 groups preliminarily divided into Placebo Group (PG n=59), Minimum Intervention Group (Ca 500mg/day Group n=58) and Maximum Intervention Group (Ca 1,500mg/day Group n =58). In the follow-up after four weeks, there were 44 losses, 12 in the RG, 15 in the minimum intervention group and 17 in the maximum intervention group. In the eight-week follow-up, there were 48 losses, 15 in the PG, 16 in the GIMin and 17 in the GIMax. In the analysis of the total number of pregnant women who started the research protocol, 83 completed all the steps, being 32 participants in the GP, 27 in the GIMin and 24 in the GIMax.</i_freetext>
        <results_actual_enrolment/>
        <results_date_completed>15/09/2020</results_date_completed>
        <results_url_link/>
        <results_summary>Pregnant women with hypertensive disorders are at increased risk of chronic inflammation, cardiovascular disease, endothelial dysfunction, dyslipidemia, preeclampsia, among other events. The dilemma posed by the best dosage of calcium supplementation on these factors is evident. This study aimed to analyze the effects of calcium supplementation on blood pressure levels and proteinuria, as well as cardiovascular and inflammatory markers over time, comparing the use of high and low-dose calcium in hypertensive pregnant women from June 2018 to July. de 2019. This is a randomized clinical trial with three parallel groups, placebo controlled, carried out at the referral outpatient clinic for high-risk prenatal care in the southern region of Brazil with a three-stage follow-up analysis. The intervention consisted of calcium intake 500mg/day, calcium 1,500mg/day and placebo. Data were analyzed according to a generalized mixed equation estimation model adopting α 0.05. The effect of low- and high-dose calcium on outcome over time was maintained between groups, even after adjusting for confounders. There was a significant difference in the parameters analyzed in the time and group interaction (p &lt;0.000). In the intragroup evaluation, we observed a decrease in the means of 12.3 mmHg in SBP (p intragroup =0.000), 9.2 mmHg in DBP (p intragroup =0.000), 36 mg/dl triglyceride (p intragroup =0.017) and 8.8 mg/ dl hs-CRP (p intragroup =0.000), 37 mg/dl creatinine (p intergroup 0.002), 4.8 mg/dl proteinuria (p intergroup 0.000), 4.5 pg/dl PTH (p intergroup 0.009). After 8 weeks of supplement use, the differences were in the mean blood pressure levels and other cardiovascular risk markers in both intervention groups, when compared with the placebo group. At the end of treatment, there was a significant reduction of 8.4 mmHg in SBP and 7.1 mmHg in DBP for the calcium 500mg/day group and a reduction of 10.9 mmHg in SBP and 8.8 mmHg in DBP for the group calcium 1,500mg/day. Calcium improved cardiovascular prognosis in hypertensive pregnant women by reducing blood pressure levels, inflammatory markers and adjusting the lipid profile. Daily calcium supplementation seems to be favorable even in short-term use and low dosage in women with low dietary nutrient intake and in developing countries.</results_summary>
        <results_date_posted/>
        <results_date_first_publication/>
        <results_baseline_char>In the analysis of the total number of pregnant women who started the research protocol, 83 completed all the steps. The results suggest that randomization was not compromised by discrepancies between groups. At the end of the study, after 8 weeks, poor adherence to treatment was significant for the maximal supplementation group.</results_baseline_char>
        <results_participant_flow>In the recruitment and allocation of 193 eligible participants, 05 were excluded before randomization for not meeting the inclusion criteria, 11 refused to participate and 02 had severe anemia. Thus, 175 pregnant women were randomized and randomly allocated into 3 groups preliminarily divided into Placebo Group (PG n=59), Minimum Intervention Group (Ca 500mg/day Group n=58) and Maximum Intervention Group (Ca 1,500mg/day Group n =58). In the follow-up after four weeks, there were 44 losses, 12 in the RG, 15 in the minimum intervention group and 17 in the maximum intervention group. In the analysis of the total number of pregnant women who started the research protocol, 83 completed all the steps.</results_participant_flow>
        <results_adverse_events>Every week, the groups were accompanied by a research assistant to monitor the safety of the participants. In the presence of serious adverse events such as hypertensive peaks, severe preeclampsia, eclampsia, Hellp Syndrome, the participants were duly referred to the hospital units and treated. Such events were not observed throughout the study.</results_adverse_events>
        <results_outcome_measures/>
        <results_url_protocol/>
        <results_IPD_plan>No</results_IPD_plan>
        <results_IPD_description/>
      </main>
      <contacts>
        <contact>
          <type>public</type>
          <firstname>Erica </firstname>
          <middlename>de Brito </middlename>
          <lastname>Pitilin</lastname>
          <address/>
          <city>Chapecó</city>
          <country1>Brazil</country1>
          <zip>89802-112</zip>
          <telephone>+55-049-20493100</telephone>
          <email>erica.pitilin@gmail.com</email>
          <affiliation>Universidade Federal da Fronteira Sul</affiliation>
        </contact>
        <contact>
          <type>public</type>
          <firstname>Janine</firstname>
          <middlename/>
          <lastname>Schirmer</lastname>
          <address>Rua Napoleão 754</address>
          <city>São Paulo</city>
          <country1>Brazil</country1>
          <zip>04024-002</zip>
          <telephone>+55-011-55764430</telephone>
          <email>schirmer.jane@gmail.com</email>
          <affiliation>Universidade Federal de São Paulo</affiliation>
        </contact>
        <contact>
          <type>scientific</type>
          <firstname>Erica </firstname>
          <middlename>de Brito </middlename>
          <lastname>Pitilin</lastname>
          <address/>
          <city>Chapecó</city>
          <country1>Brazil</country1>
          <zip>89802-112</zip>
          <telephone>+55-049-20493100</telephone>
          <email>erica.pitilin@gmail.com</email>
          <affiliation>Universidade Federal da Fronteira Sul</affiliation>
        </contact>
      </contacts>
      <countries>
        <country2>Brazil</country2>
      </countries>
      <criteria>
        <inclusion_criteria>Pregnant women over 18 years of age; single fetus; primigravidae; diagnosis of gestational hypertension; overweight and/or obesity; be at least 20 weeks pregnant; low socioeconomic factor; low dietary calcium intake (less than 800mg/day); non-use of drugs that interfere with calcium absorption (corticosteroids; thiazides; thyroid hormones)</inclusion_criteria>
        <agemin>18Y</agemin>
        <agemax>49Y</agemax>
        <gender>F</gender>
        <exclusion_criteria>Pregnant women with polyhydramnios; severe anemia; fetal death; severe preeclampsia; history of hypertension before pregnancy; placental abruption; premature rupture of membranes; abnormal umbilical artery doppler; uteroplacental insufficiency; other pre-existing medical condition; any contraindication to calcium supplementation</exclusion_criteria>
      </criteria>
      <health_condition_code>
        <hc_code>O00-O99</hc_code>
      </health_condition_code>
      <intervention_code>
        <i_code/>
      </intervention_code>
      <intervention_keyword>
        <i_keyword>G07.203.300.456</i_keyword>
        <i_keyword>D01.146.275</i_keyword>
      </intervention_keyword>
      <primary_outcome>
        <prim_outcome>1- Expected outcome: It is expected to find a significant difference in the intragroup (calcium 500mg/day, calcium 1,500mg/day and placebo group) and intergroup analysis (before the intervention, 4 weeks after and 8 weeks after) with blood pressure reduction systolic blood pressure (SBP) over time.</prim_outcome>
        <prim_outcome>1- Outcome found: A difference was found between the groups after 8 weeks of supplementation. There was a reduction in systolic blood pressure (SBP) for the supplemented groups when compared to the placebo group (intergroup analysis p&lt; 0.05). Furthermore, there was a significant reduction of 9.4 mmHg in SBP (intragroup analysis p&lt;0.05) after 8 weeks for the calcium 1,500mg/day group and a reduction of 12.3 mmHg for the calcium 500mg/day group.</prim_outcome>
        <prim_outcome>2- Expected outcome: It is expected to find a significant difference in the intragroup (calcium 500mg/day, calcium 1,500mg/day and placebo group) and intergroup analysis (before the intervention, 4 weeks after and 8 weeks after) with blood pressure reduction diastolic blood pressure (DBP) over time.</prim_outcome>
        <prim_outcome>2- Outcome found: A difference was found between the groups after 8 weeks of supplementation. There was a reduction in diastolic blood pressure (DBP) for the group supplemented with calcium 500mg/day when compared with the placebo group (intergroup analysis p&lt; 0.05). Still, there was a significant reduction of 9.2 mmHg after 8 weeks (intragroup analysis p&lt;0.05). There were no significant differences for the 1,500mg/day calcium group.</prim_outcome>
      </primary_outcome>
      <secondary_outcome>
        <sec_outcome>3- Expected outcome: It is expected to find a significant difference in the intragroup (calcium 500mg/day, calcium 1,500mg/day and placebo group) and intergroup analysis (before the intervention, 4 weeks after and 8 weeks after) with a reduction in proteinuria over over time</sec_outcome>
        <sec_outcome>3- Outcome found: A difference was found between the groups after 8 weeks of supplementation. There was a reduction in proteinuria of 7.2 mg/dl for the calcium 500mg/day group (p=0.002) and a 4.5mg/dl reduction in proteinuria for the calcium 1,500mg/day group (p&lt;0.05) when compared with the placebo group.</sec_outcome>
        <sec_outcome>4- Expected outcome: It is expected to find a significant difference in the intragroup (calcium 500mg/day, calcium 1,500mg/day and placebo group) and intergroup analysis (before the intervention, 4 weeks after and 8 weeks after) with a reduction in urinary creatinine over time.</sec_outcome>
        <sec_outcome>4- Outcome found: A difference was found between the groups after 8 weeks of supplementation. There was a reduction in urinary creatinine of 3.2 mg/dl for the calcium 500mg/day group (p=0.008) and 8.6 mg/dl of creatinine for the calcium 1,500mg/day group (p&lt;0.05) when compared with the placebo group.</sec_outcome>
        <sec_outcome>5- Expected outcome: It is expected to find a significant difference in the intragroup (calcium 500mg/day, calcium 1,500mg/day and placebo group) and intergroup analysis (before the intervention, 4 weeks after and 8 weeks after) with parathyroid hormone reduction ( PTH) over time.</sec_outcome>
        <sec_outcome>5- Outcome found: A difference was found between the groups after 8 weeks of supplementation. There was a reduction in PTH of 4.7 pg/ml for the calcium 500mg/day group (p&lt;0.05) and 3.1 mg/dl of PTH for the calcium 1,500mg/day group (p&lt;0.05) when compared with the placebo group.</sec_outcome>
        <sec_outcome>6- Expected outcome: It is expected to find a significant difference in the intragroup (calcium 500mg/day, calcium 1,500mg/day and placebo group) and intergroup analysis (before the intervention, 4 weeks after and 8 weeks after) with an increase in blood calcium over time.</sec_outcome>
        <sec_outcome>6- Outcome found: A difference was found between the groups after 8 weeks of supplementation. There were increased blood calcium concentrations for both supplemented groups when compared to the placebo group.</sec_outcome>
        <sec_outcome>7- Expected outcome: It is expected to find a significant difference in the intragroup (calcium 500mg/day, calcium 1,500mg/day and placebo group) and intergroup analysis (before the intervention, 4 weeks after and 8 weeks after) with total cholesterol reduction over time.</sec_outcome>
        <sec_outcome>7- Outcome found: A difference was found after 8 weeks of supplementation for the 1,500mg/day calcium group when compared to the placebo group. Still, there was a reduction of 65.8 mg/dl of cholesterol (p&lt;0.05). As for the calcium 500mg/day group, there were no significant differences</sec_outcome>
        <sec_outcome>8- Expected outcome: It is expected to find a significant difference in the intragroup (calcium 500mg/day, calcium 1,500mg/day and placebo group) and intergroup (before the intervention, 4 weeks after and 8 weeks after) over time.</sec_outcome>
        <sec_outcome>8- Outcome found: A difference was found between the groups after 8 weeks of supplementation when compared with the placebo group. There was a significant reduction of 36 mg/dl in the calcium 500mg/day group and a reduction of 51.2 mg/dl for the calcium 1,500mg/day group after 8 weeks.</sec_outcome>
        <sec_outcome>9- Expected outcome: It is expected to find a significant difference in the intragroup (calcium 500mg/day, calcium 1,500mg/day and placebo group) and intergroup analysis (before the intervention, 4 weeks after and 8 weeks after) with a reduction in protein C -ultrasensitive reactive (hs-PCR) over time.</sec_outcome>
        <sec_outcome>9- Outcome found: A difference was found between the groups after 8 weeks of supplementation when compared with the placebo group. There was a significant reduction of 8.8 mg/dl in hs-CRP in the calcium 500mg/day group and a reduction of 6.5 mg/dl for the calcium 1,500mg/day group after 8 weeks.</sec_outcome>
        <sec_outcome>10- Expected outcome: It is expected to find a significant difference in the intragroup (calcium 500mg/day, calcium 1,500mg/day and placebo group) and intergroup analysis (before the intervention, 4 weeks after and 8 weeks after) with a reduction in the fractions of the cholesterol such as low-density lipoprotein (LDL) and high-density lipoprotein (HDL) over time.</sec_outcome>
        <sec_outcome>10- Outcome found: No differences were found between groups after 8 weeks of supplementation in cholesterol fractions such as HDL or LDL over time.</sec_outcome>
        <sec_outcome>11- Expected outcome: It is expected to find a significant difference in the intragroup (calcium 500mg/day, calcium 1500mg/day and placebo group) and intergroup (before the intervention, 4 weeks after and 8 weeks after) over time.</sec_outcome>
        <sec_outcome>11- Outcome found: No differences were found between groups after 8 weeks of supplementation in urea concentrations over time.</sec_outcome>
      </secondary_outcome>
      <secondary_sponsor>
        <sponsor_name>Universidade Federal da Fronteira Sul</sponsor_name>
        <sponsor_name/>
      </secondary_sponsor>
      <secondary_ids/>
      <secondary_id>
        <sec_id>81829417.3.0000.5505</sec_id>
        <issuing_authority>Plataforma Brasil</issuing_authority>
      </secondary_id>
      <secondary_id>
        <sec_id/>
        <issuing_authority/>
      </secondary_id>
      <secondary_id>
        <sec_id>2.659.764</sec_id>
        <issuing_authority>Comitê de Ética em Pesquisa com Seres Humanos da Universidade Federal de São Paulo</issuing_authority>
      </secondary_id>
      <secondary_id>
        <sec_id/>
        <issuing_authority/>
      </secondary_id>
      <source_support>
        <source_name>Fundo de Apoio à Manutenção e ao Desenvolvimento da Educação Superior</source_name>
        <source_name/>
        <source_name>Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico</source_name>
        <source_name/>
      </source_support>
      <ethics_reviews>
        <ethics_review>
          <status>Approved</status>
          <approval_date>17/05/2018</approval_date>
          <contact_name>Comitê de Ética em Pesquisa Universidade Federal de São Paulo  </contact_name>
          <contact_address>Rua Francisco de Castro, 55</contact_address>
          <contact_phone>(11)5571-1062</contact_phone>
          <contact_email>cep@unifesp.edu.br</contact_email>
        </ethics_review>
      </ethics_reviews>
    </trial>
  </trials>
</root>
